危险区域
禁止入内
小心
哭泣的天使
噢 还有蹲下!
真的 快蹲下!
莎丽·斯帕罗
蹲下  现在
马上蹲下
小心哭泣的天使
来自博士的问候 1969年
神秘博士第三季第十集
别眨眼
编剧 史蒂文·莫法特
凯茜
Kathy?
听好 你的性命可能全靠这个了
DOCTOR: Listen, your life could depend on this.
别眨眼 一下都不能眨 一眨眼你就会死
Don't blink. Don't even blink. Blink and you're dead.
它们很快 比你想像的要快
They are fast. Faster than you can believe.
别转身 别回头 千万别眨眼
Don't turn your back, don't look away and don't blink.
祝你好运
Good luck.
喂
Hello?
受了点惊吓 想聊聊 帮你煮咖啡呢
Bit freaked. Need to talk. Making you a coffee.
莎丽·斯帕罗 现在是凌晨一点
Sally Sparrow, it's 1:00 in the morning.
你认为我会在凌晨一点出门吗
Do you think I'm going out at 1:00 in the morning?
不
No.
我在厨房
I'm in the kitchen.
你客厅那些屏幕是怎么回事
What's that on all those screens in your front room?
噢 老天
Oh, God.
噢 老天 莎丽
Oh, God. Sally,
你还没遇到我哥哥拉瑞吧
you've met my brother Larry, haven't you?
没有
No.
你会的
You 're about to.
好吧
Okay.
我不确定
Not sure,
但真的 真的希望…
but really, really hoping…
我穿着裤子吗
Pants?
没有
No.
快穿上
Put them on!
快穿上 我恨你
Put them on! I hate you!
你在想什么
What are you thinking?
对不起
Sorry.
我的蠢蛋哥哥
My useless brother.
莎丽 怎么了
Sally? What's wrong?
发生了什么
What's happened?
危险区域
禁止入内
很好 开始调查吧
Okay. Let's investigate.
你和我 女子侦查队
You and me, girl investigators.
我喜欢
Love it. Hey!
嘿 "麻雀和夜莺"
Hey! Sparrow and Nightingale.
太合拍了
That so works.
像ITV侦探剧似的
Bit ITV.
我知道
I know!
话说 你上次来这里干嘛
What did you come here for anyway?
我喜欢古老的东西
I love old things.
它们使我伤感
They make me feel sad.
伤感有什么好的
What's good about sad?
对深沉的人来说就是快乐
It's happy for deep people.
哭泣天使
The weeping angel.
我的花园里可不会放这个
KATHY: Wouldn't have that in my garden.
它动过了
It's moved
它怎么了
It's what?
跟昨晚比
Since yesterday.
我确定 它更近了
I'm sure of it. It's closer.
它离房子更近了
It's got closer to the house.
我的名字怎么会被写在这里
How can my name be written here?
这怎么可能
How is that possible?
谁会来这里
Who'd come here?
你在干什么 可能是小偷
What are you doing? It could be a burglar.
小偷会摇门铃吗
A burglar who rings the doorbell?
好吧 我留在这里以防…
Okay. I'll stay here in case of…
以防什么
In case of?
以防万一
Incidents?
好吧
Okay.
我在找莎丽·斯帕罗
I'm looking for Sally Sparrow.
你怎么知道我会在这里
How did you know I'd be here?
有人委托我把这封信带来
I was told to bring this letter
在今天 这个确切的时刻
on this date at this exact time
送给莎丽·斯帕罗
to Sally Sparrow.
看起来很旧
Looks old.
本来就很旧
It is old.
不好意思
I'm sorry,
你身上有没有带着照片
do you have anything with a photograph on it
比如驾照之类的
like a driving license?
怎么有人知道我会来 我没告诉过任何人
No one knew I was coming here. I didn't tell anyone.
怎么可能有人知道
How could anyone have known?
这有点复杂
MAN: It's all a bit complicated.
我都不确定自己是否理解
I'm not sure I understand it myself.
对不起 这可能有点傻
Sorry, I feel really stupid.
但委托人说必须完全确认
I was told to make absolutely sure.
这么小的照片挺难分辨的 对吧
It's so hard to tell with these little photographs, isn't it?
很显然
Apparently.
那么
Well,
我觉得应该没错
here goes, I suppose.
感觉真奇怪 过了这么多年
Funny feeling after all these years.
是谁寄来的
Who's it from?
那是个很长的故事
Well, that's a long story, actually.
告诉我名字
Give me a name.
凯瑟琳·温赖特
Katherine Wainwright
但她特别嘱咐我告诉你
But she specified I should tell you that,
在她结婚前
prior to marriage
[英文的"南丁格尔" 即 "夜莺"]
她叫做凯茜·南丁格尔
she was called Kathy Nightingale.
凯茜
Kathy?
凯茜 没错
Kathy. Yes.
凯瑟琳·凯斯特洛·南丁格尔
Katherine Costello Nightingale
这是个玩笑吗
Is this a joke?
玩笑
Joke?
凯茜 是你搞的吗
Kathy, is this you?
很好笑
Very funny.
凯茜
Kathy?
凯茜 凯茜
Kathy? Kathy?
拜托你
Please.
请一定要收下这个
You need to take this.
我答应过她的
I promised.
打扰一下
Excuse me.
我在哪里
Where am I?
我刚刚在伦敦
I was in London.
我刚刚在伦敦市中心
I was in the middle of London.
你在赫尔
You're in Hull
我不在
No, I'm not.
这里是赫尔
This is Hull.
才不是
No, it isn't.
你在赫尔
You're in Hull.
我不在赫尔 别再说赫尔了
I'm not in Hull. Stop saying Hull.
你是谁
Who are you?
你为什么在这里
Why are you here?
我答应过她
I made a promise.
答应过谁
Who to?
我的祖母
My grandmother.
凯瑟琳·凯斯特洛·南丁格尔
Katherine Costello Nightingale.
伦敦可没这个 这上面没有叫这个的
Don't have that in London. There's no call for it.
都是赫尔
It's all Hull.
1920年
你的祖母
Your grandmother?
是的
Yes.
她20年前就去世了
She died 20 years ago.
哼
Huh.
难道她们是亲戚
So they're related?
什么
Sorry?
我的凯茜和你的祖母
My Kathy, your grandmother.
她们长得一模一样
They're practically identical.
你要去哪里
Where you going?
我亲爱的莎丽·斯帕罗
My dearest Sally Sparrow
如果我的孙子履行了他的承诺
if my grandson has done as he promises he will
那么你读到这封信时
then as you read these words
对你来说 几分钟前我们才说过话
it has been mere minutes since we last spoke,for you.
对我来说 已经过了60多年
For me, it has been over 60 years.
第三张照片是我的孩子们
The third of the photographs is of my children.
最小的叫做莎丽
The youngest is Sally.
当然 是按照你的名字起的
I named her after you, of course.
这太过分了
This is sick.
实在太过分了
This is totally sick.
凯茜
Kathy?
Kathy!
凯茜
Kathy?
不 别走 等等
No, wait. Hang on!
我猜 除非我能非常长寿
I suppose, unless I live to a really exceptional old age
否则你读到这信时我一定早已去世
I will be long gone as you read this.
别为我难过
Don't feel sorry for me.
我过的很幸福很充实
I have lea' a good and full life.
我爱上了一个好人
I've loved a good man
也受到了他的真心对待
and been well loved in return.
你会喜欢本的
You would have liked Ben.
他是我在1920年遇到的第一个人
He was the very first person I met in 1920.
你在跟踪我吗
Are you following me?
是的
Yeah.
你能别跟着我了吗
Are you going to stop following me?
不 我想不会
No, I don't think so.
才在2007年吸了一口气
To take one breath in 2007
又在1920年呼出来
and the next in 1920
真是一种奇特的开始新生活的方式
is a strange way to start a new life
但新生活正是我一直想要的
but a new life is exactly what I've always wanted.
你骗他你18岁 你这个小骗子
You told him you were 18, you lying cow.
你那个时候我父母已经去世
My mum and dad are gone by your time,
所以只能跟劳伦斯说了
so really there's only Lawrence to tell.
他在女王大街的DVD商店工作
He works at the DVD store on Queen Street.
我不知道你要怎么跟他说
I don't know what you're gonna say to him
但我知道你会想到办法的
but I know you'll think of something.
请告诉他我爱他
just tell him I love him.
打扰了 我找劳伦斯·南丁格尔
Excuse me. I'm looking for  Lowrence Nightinggale.
在后面
In the back.
有人吗
Hello?
玛莎
Martha!
对不起
Sorry.
很有可能
Quite possibly.
恐怕是这样
Afraid so.
噢
Oh.
你好
Hello.
有什么事吗
Can I help you?
你好
Hi.
三十八
Thirty-eight
噢 等一下
just a moment.
等等 我们见过 是吗
Hang on. We've met, haven't we?
你会想起来的
It'll come to you.
噢 我的老天
Oh, my God.
没错
There it is.
对不起 再次抱歉上次…
Sorry. Sorry, again, about the whole…
你妹妹的消息
Message from your sister.
哦 好的
Oh, okay.
什么
What?
她的消息是什么
What is it? What's the message?
她要离开一段时间
She's had to go away for a bit.
去哪里
Where?
只是工作上的事 没什么好担心的
Just a work thing. Nothing to worry about.
好吧
Okay.
还有…
And…
还有什么
And… And what?
她爱你
She loves you.
她什么
She what?
她是这么说的 她只是顺便提到
She said to say… She just sort of mentioned it.
她爱你 很好 不是吗
She loves you. There, that's nice, isn't it?
她病了吗
Is she ill?
不 没有
No! No.
是我病了吗
Am I ill?
不是
No.
是个恶作剧吗
Is this a trick?
不是 她爱你
No. She loves you.
呃…人们不理解时间
People don't understand time.
它跟你们想的不一样
It's not what you think it is.
这个人是谁
Who is this guy?
对不起 暂停老是失灵
Sorry, the pause thing keeps slipping.
蠢东西
Stupid thing.
昨晚在凯茜家
Last night at Kathy's
你那些屏幕里也有他 同一个人
you had him on all those screens, that same guy.
一直在说些什么
Talking about,
眨眼之类的东西
I don't know, blinking or something.
是的 眨眼那段不错
Yeah, the bit about the blinking's great.
我正在看它们是不是全都一样
I was just checking to see if they were all the same.
什么一样
What were the same?
这是什么 他是谁
What is this? Who is he?
一个彩蛋
An Easter egg.
你说什么
Excuse me?
就像DVD花絮 知道吗
Like a DVD extra, yeah?
你知道在DVD里
You know how on DVDs
会有花絮访谈和幕后片段吧
they put extras, you know, documentaries and stuff?
有时候这些片段是隐藏起来的
Sometimes they put on hidden ones
他们称之为彩蛋
and they call them Easter eggs.
你得去找它们
You have to go looking for them
根据主菜单里的一堆线索
follow a bunch of clues on the menu screen.
很复杂
Complicated.
对不起
Sorry.
有意思的是
It's interesting, actually.
他出现在17张不同的DVD上
He is on 17 different DVDs.
17张完全不相干的DVD上 都有他的片段
There are 17 totally unrelated DVDs all with him on
都是隐藏起来的 都是秘密
always hidden away, always a secret.
甚至出版商也不知道
Not even the publishers know.
我跟制片商也谈过 连他们也不知道
I've talked to the manufacturers, right? They don't even know.
他就像是一个鬼魂DVD花絮
He's like… He's a ghost DVD extra.
在他不该出现的地方冒出来
Just shows up where he's not supposed to be.
但只在那些17张DVD上
But only on those. Those 17.
他在做什么
Well, what does he do?
就坐在那里 说些奇怪的话
Just sits there, making random remarks.
好像我们在听一段交谈的一半
It's like we're hearing half a conversation.
我和伙计们一直想找出另外一半
Me and the guys are always trying to work out the other half.
你说你和伙计们 你是指网上那些人对吧
When you say you and the guys, you mean the internet, don't you?
你怎么知道的
How'd you know?
真诡异 不是吗
Spooky, isn't it?
非常复杂
Very complicated.
劳伦斯 来帮忙
Lawrence, need you.
抱歉离开一会儿
Excuse me a sec.
人们认为时间是严格按照因果顺序进行的
People assume that time is a strict progression of cause to effect
但事实上从非线性 非主观的观点来看
but actually, from a non-linear, non-subjective viewpoint
时间更像是一大团弯弯绕绕 颠颠倒倒的...东西
it's more like a big ball of wibbly-wobbly, timey-wimey stuff.
这个句子起得不错
It started well, that sentence.
后面就跑偏了
It got away from me, yeah.
好吧 这有点诡异
Okay, that was weird.
就好像你能听到我
Like you can hear me.
是啊 我是能听到你
Well, I can hear you.
好了 够了
Okay, that's enough.
我受够了 我今天已经很不顺了
I've had enough now. I've had a long day.
我真的是受够了
and I've had bloody enough.
对不起
Sorry,
今天不太顺心
bad day.
给你找了名单
Got you the list.
什么
What?
那17张DVD 我以为你会感兴趣
The 17 DVDs. I thought you might be interested.
对 很好 多谢
Yeah. Great. Thanks.
去找警察啊 你这个蠢女人
Go to the police, you stupid woman.
为什么电影里的人总是不找警察
Why does nobody ever just go to the police?
听着 我知道这听起来很疯狂
Look, I know how mad I'm sounding.
能不能请你从头开始
Shall we try it from the beginning this time?
好吧 有座房子
Okay, there's this house
古老的大房子 空了很多年
a big, old house, been empty for years
快倒塌了 院子外面写着西丘庄园
falling apart, Wester Drumlins, out by the estate.
你们也许见过
You've probably seen it.
西丘庄园
Wester Drumlins?
是的
Yes.
你在这里稍等片刻好吗
Could you just wait here for a minute?
好吧 我快崩溃了
Okay. Cracking up now.
你好
Hi.
比利·西普顿警探
Hi. DI Billy Shipton.
西丘庄园 我的案子
Wester Drumlins, that's mine.
现在不能跟你谈 有件要事不能耽误
Can't talk to you now, got a thing I can't be late for
所以如果你能…
so if you could just…
你好
Hello.
嗯 马西
Er, Marcie,
你能不能告诉他们
Er, Marcie, can you tell them
我要晚点再处理那件要事
I'm going to be late for that thing?
全都是
All of them?
过去两年里的 没错
over the last two years, yeah.
这些车上都还有私人物品
They all still have personal items in them
有些甚至发动机都还开着
and a couple still had the motor running.
这么说过去两年里
So over the last two years
所有这些车的主人
the owners of all of these vehicles have driven up
都开车到了西丘庄园那里
have driven up to Wester Drumlins house,
把车停在外面 然后莫名消失了
parked outside and just disappeared?
那是什么
What's that?
啊 西丘庄园收藏品中的骄傲
Ah. The pride of the Wester Drumlins collection.
也是在那里发现的
We found that there, too.
我猜是某人开的玩笑
Somebody's idea of a joke, I suppose.
这是什么 警亭是什么
But what is it? What's a police box?
是种特殊的警用电话亭
Well, it's a special kind of phone box for policemen.
过去到处都有
They used to have them all over,
但这个不是真的
but this isn't a real one.
电话是假的 窗户的尺寸也不对
The phone is just a dummy and the windows are the wrong size.
连门都打不开
Can't even get in it.
很普通的耶鲁锁 但怎么也打不开
Ordinary Yale lock, but nothing fits.
但这还不是大问题
But that's not the big question.
瞧 你正在错过大问题
See, you're missing the big question.
好吧 什么大问题
Okay, what's the big question?
可以跟我去喝一杯吗
Will you have a drink with me?
你说什么
I'm sorry?
喝一杯 你和我
Drink? You, me,
现在
now?
你不是在工作吗
Aren't you on duty,
西普顿警探
Detective Inspector Shipton?
不 我早就收工了
Nope. Knocked off before I left.
我告诉他们我家里有急事
Told them I had a family crisis.
为什么
Why?
因为生命很短暂 而你又很性感
Because life is short and you are hot.
喝一杯
Drink?
不
No.
以后呢
Ever?
也许
Maybe.
电话号码
Phone number?
进展太快了点吧 西普顿警探
Moving rather fast, DI Shipton.
叫我比利 我已经下班了
Billy. I'm off duty.
可不是嘛
Aren't you just?
那是你的电话号码
Is that your phone number?
只是我的电话号码
Just my phone number.
不是承诺 不是保证
Not a promise, not a guarantee,
不是约定 就是个电话号码
not an IOU, just a phone number.
你叫莎丽…
And that's Sally…
莎丽·西普顿
Sally Shipton
是斯帕罗
Sparrow!
莎丽·斯帕罗
Sally Sparrow
我要走了 别看我
Okay, going now. Don't look at me.
我会打给你 -别看我
I'll phone you. - Don't look at me.
明天打给你 -别看我
Phone you tomorrow. - Don't look at me.
也许今晚就打给你
Might even phone you tonight.
别看我
Don't look at me.
绝对会打给你 美女
Definitely gonna phone you, gorgeous girl.
随便你啦
Definitely better.
很普通的耶鲁锁 但怎么也打不开
SHIPTON: Ordinary Yale lock, but nothing fits.
欢迎你
DOCTOR: Welcome.
我在哪里
Where am I?
1969年
1969.
还不算糟 你可以期待人类登陆月球
Not bad, as it goes. You've got the moon landing to look forward to.
登月太好玩了
Oh, the moon landing's brilliant!
我们去过四次
We went four times.
那时我们的交通工具还在
Back when we had transport.
正在想办法
Working on it.
我怎么到这里来的
How did I get here?
跟我们来的方式一样
Same way we did.
天使之触
Touch of an angel.
可能是同一个 因为你来到同一年
Same one, probably, since you ended up in the same year.
不不不不 别起来
No, no, no. Don't get up.
不用时空舱的时间旅行 很危险
Time travel without a capsule, nasty.
先喘口气 半小时内别去游泳
Catch your breath, don't go swimming for half an hour.
我不游泳 我不会游
I don't… I can't…
迷人的种族 哭泣天使
Fascinating race, the weeping angels.
宇宙中唯一一种让人善终的疯子
The only psychopaths in the universe to kill you nicely.
干净利落 不留痕迹
No mess, no fuss,
就这样把你踢到过去 让你老死
they just zap you into the past and let you live to death
你的余生在眨眼间就消逝了
the rest of your life used up and blown away in the blink of an eye.
你在过去死去
You die in the past
而它们留在当时吸收
and in the present they consume
你拥有的时间能量
the energy of all the days you might have had.
所有被偷走的时间
All your stolen moments.
它们是偷窃的生物 它们靠势能生存
They're creatures of the abstract, they live off potential energy.
你到底在说些什么
What in God's name are you talking about?
相信我 当他停下喘口气时你点头就是了
Trust me, just nod when he stops for breath.
用这个找到你的
Tracked you down with this.
这个是我的"时间错乱"探测器
This is my timey-wimey detector.
发现异常它就会发出"叮"的声音
lso, it can boil an egg at 30 paces.
也能使30步以内的鸡蛋煮熟
Also, it can boil an egg at 30 paces.
而且根本控制不住
Whether you want it to or not, actually
所以我已学会远离母鸡了
so I've learnt to stay away from hens.
母鸡爆炸可不太好看
It's not pretty when they blow.
我不明白 我在哪里
I don't understand. Where am I?
1969年 如他所说
1969, like he said.
通常我会载你回家
Normally, I'd offer you a lift home,
不过这次我的车被偷了
but somebody nicked my motor.
所以我需要你带个话给莎丽·斯帕罗
So I need you to take a message to Sally Sparrow.
我很抱歉 比利
And I'm sorry, Billy,
我真的真的很抱歉
I am very, very sorry.
这得耗费你很长一段时间
It's gonna take you a while.
喂
Hello?
比利 你在哪里
Billy, where are you?
什么
Where?
比利
Billy?
我们见面那天也在下雨
It was raining when we met.
这就是刚刚那场雨
It's the same rain.
她看起来不错
She looks nice.
她也叫莎丽
Her name was Sally, too.
莎丽·西普顿
Sally Shipton.
Sally Shipton!
我经常想着早一点来找你
I often thought about looking for you before tonight.
但显然那会在时空结构上捅出一个大洞
But apparently it would have torn a hole in the fabric of space and time
并且摧毁宇宙的三分之二
and destroyed two thirds of the universe.
而且
Also,
还会使我秃顶
I'd lost my hair.
宇宙的三分之二 谁告诉你的
Two thirds of the universe? Where'd you get that from?
有个人在1969年 叫我给你带个话
There's a man in 1969. He sent me with a message for you.
什么人
What man?
博士
The Doctor.
带的话是什么
And what was the message?
只有这个
just this
"看看名单"
"look at the list".
那是什么意思
What does that mean?
只有这点 "看看名单"
Is that it? Look at the list?
他说你现在应该有名单了
He said you'd have it by now.
17张DVD的名单
A list of 17 DVDs.
我在过去并没做警察
I didn't stay a policeman back then.
而是从事了出版业
Got into publishing,
然后是视频出版
then video publishing.
然后…当然是DVD出版
Then DVDs, of course.
是你把彩蛋加进去的
You put the Easter egg on.
你注意到那17张DVD的共同点了吗
Have you noticed what all 17 DVDs have in common yet?
我猜那对你有点难
I suppose it's hard for you in a way.
博士怎么知道我有名单
How could the Doctor have even known I had a list?
我才刚刚拿到
I only just got this.
我问过他
I asked him how
但他说 他没办法告诉我
but he said he couldn't tell me.
他说有一天你会明白的
He said you'd understand it one day
但我…永远不能
but that I never would.
我一明白就回来告诉你
Soon as I understand it, I'll come and tell you.
不用了 美女
No, gorgeous girl.
你不能
You can't.
我只剩下今晚了
There's only tonight.
多年前他告诉我
He told me all those years ago,
我们会再次相遇
that we'll only meet again
只能是这一次
this one time.
在我死去的那个晚上
On the night I die.
噢 比利
Oh, Billy.
这一直支撑着我
It's kept me going.
我现在又老又病
I'm an old, sick man.
但还有一件事值得我去期待
But I've had something to look forward to.
生命如此漫长 你却美丽依然
Ah, life is long and you are hot.
看看我的手
Look at my hands.
这双老人的手
An old man's hands.
这到底是怎么发生的
How did that happen?
我会留在这儿
I'll stay.
我留下来陪你 好吗
I'm gonna stay with you, okay?
谢谢你 莎丽·斯帕罗
Thank you, Sally Sparrow.
雨停之后就是我的尽头
I have till the rain stops.
Banto小店
Bantos.
它们是我的
They're mine.
什么
What?
名单上的17张DVD
The DVDs on the list, the 17 DVDs,
它们的共同点就是我
what they've got in common is me.
这些DVD都属于我
They're all the DVDs I own.
那个彩蛋是设计来给我的
The Easter egg was intended for me.
总共只有17张DVD吗
You've only got 17 DVDs?
你有没有便携式DVD播放机
Do you have a portable DVD player?
当然有 怎么了
Of course. Why?
我要你跟我碰面
I want you to meet me.
在哪里
Where?
西丘庄园
Wester Drumlin
我就知道你家会像史酷比家一样阴森
I knew you would live in Scooby Doo's house.
拜托 我不住在这里
For God's sake, I don't live here.
这张是声音最清晰的
This is the one with the clearest sound.
这张画质更好一点
Slightly better picture quality on this one
但我不知道… -无关紧要
but I don't know… - Doesn't matter.
好吧
Okay.
他出来了
There he is.
博士
The Doctor.
博士是谁
Who's a doctor?
他就是博士
He's the Doctor.
没错 就是我
Yup, that's me.
好吧 这挺吓人的
Okay, that was scary.
不 听起来像是他在回答你
No, it sounds like he's replying
但他每次都是这么说的
but he always says that.
是的 没错
Yes, I do.
还有这句
And that.
是的 这句也是
Yup. And this.
他能听见我们
He can hear us.
天哪 你真的能听见我们
Oh, my God. You can really hear us.
他当然听不见我们
Of course he can't hear us.
你看
Look.
我有抄本 瞧
I've got a transcript, see?
他说的每句话
Everything he says.
"没错 就是我" "是的 没错"
"Yup, that's me." "Yes, I do."
"是的 这句也是" 下一句是…
"Yup, and this." Next, it's…
你打算读完一整篇
BOTH: Are you gonna read out the whole thing?
对不起
Sorry.
你是谁
Who are you?
我是个时间旅行者
I'm a time traveller.
或者说曾经是
or! I was.
我被困在1969年了
I'm stuck in 1969.
"我们"被困住了
We 're stuck.
他答应过带我到所有时间和空间
All of space and time, he promised me.
现在我却要在店里工作来养活他
Now I've got a job in a shop. I've gotta support him!
玛莎
Martha!
对不起
Sorry.
这段我以前看过
I've seen this bit before.
很有可能
Quite possibly.
1969年 你是在那里说话吗
1969, that's where you're talking from?
恐怕是的
Afraid so.
但你在回答我
But you're replying to me.
你不可能知道我会说什么
You can't know exactly what I'm gonna say
在我说之前40年
40 years before I say it.
38年
38.
我要把这些写下来 我要把你的话写下来
I'm getting this down. I'm writing in your bits.
怎么做到的
How?
这怎么可能 告诉我
How is this possible? Tell me.
别那么快
Not so fast.
人们不了解时间 它不是你们想像的那样子
People don't understand time. It's not what you think it is.
那它是什么样的
Then what is it?
很复杂
Complicated.
告诉我
Tell me.
非常复杂
Very complicated.
我很聪明 我在听着
I'm clever and I'm listening.
别故作高深了 因为已经有人死了
And don't patronise me because people have died
而我并不高兴
and I'm not happy.
告诉我
Tell me.
人们假定时间是严格按照因果顺序进行的
People assume that time is a strict progression of cause to effect
但事实上从非线性 非主观的观点来看
but actually, from a non-linear, non-subjective viewpoint
时间更像是一个弯弯曲曲变化无常的大球
it's more like a big ball of wibbly-wobbly, timey-wimey stuffi.
是的 我以前看到过这段
Yeah, I've seen this bit before.
你说那句话是你脱口而出的
You said that sentence got away from you.
脱口而出了 是啊
It got away from me, yeah.
下一句你要说的是 "是啊 我能听到你"
Next thing you're gonna say is, "Well, I can hear you."
是啊 我能听到你
Well, I can hear you.
这不可能
This is impossible.
不 太赞了
No. It's brilliant!
其实不是真的能听见你
Well, not hear you, exactly
但是我知道你要说的每一句话
but I know everything you're gonna say.
这句总是让我毛骨悚然
Always gives me the shivers, that bit.
你怎么能知道我要说什么
How can you know what I'm gonna say?
看你的左边
Look to your left.
他说"看你的左边"是什么意思
What's he mean by "look to your left"?
我在论坛上写了一大堆
I've written tons about that in the forums.
我认为那是个政治术语
I think it's a political statement.
他说的是你 你在干什么
He means you. What are you doing?
记录你说的话
I'm writing in your bits.
这样我就得到了一份这段对话的完整抄本
That way, I've got a complete transcript of the whole conversation.
等到这个发到网上
Wait until this hits the Net.
一定会在彩蛋论坛引起轰动
This will explode the egg forums.
我已经拿到一份完成的抄本
I've got a copy of the finished transcript,
就在我的提词机上
it's on my Autocue.
你怎么能得到一份已完成的抄本
How can you have a copy of the finished transcript?
他还在写呢
It's still being written.
我说过了 我是个时间旅行者 我从未来拿的
I told you, I'm a time traveller. I got it in the future.
好吧 让我梳理一下头绪
Okay, let me get my head round this.
你在读一份你正在进行的对话的抄本
You're reading aloud from a transcript of a conversation you're still having.
呃…时间弯弯曲曲变化无常
Wibbly-wobbly, timey-wimey…
现在别管那个了 你会速记
Actually, never mind that. You can do shorthand?
怎样
So?
重要的是我们能沟通
What matters is we can communicate.
我们现在有个大麻烦
We have got big problems now.
它们带走了蓝盒子 对不对
They have taken the blue box, haven 't they?
天使们偷走了蓝盒子
The angels have the phone box?
"天使们偷走了蓝盒子" 我最喜欢的一句
"The angels have the phone box", that's my favourite.
我要印在T恤上
I've got that on a T-shirt.
你说的天使是什么意思
What do you mean, angels?
你是说那些雕像
You mean those statue things?
来自另一个世界的生物
Creatures from another world.
但它们只是雕像啊
But they're just statues.
只有在你看见的时候是
only when you see them.
什么意思
What does that mean?
它们曾被称为"孤独的刺客"
The Lonely Assassins they used to be called.
没人清楚它们来自哪里
No one quite knows where they came from
它们跟宇宙一样古老
but they're as old as the universe
或者差不多 它们能活那么长是因为
or very nearly, and they have survived this long
它们拥有最完美的防御系统
because they have the most perfect defence system ever evolved.
它们是量子锁定的
They are quantum locked.
当被观察时它们并不存在
They don't exist when they're being observed.
它们被任何生物看到时
The moment they are seen by any other living creature
都会化为石头
they freeze into rock.
那是它们的生物特性
No choice, it's a fact of their biology.
在任何生物的视线里
In the sight of any living thing
它们完全变成石头
they literally turn to stone.
你没法杀死石头
And you can't kill a stone.
当然 石头也不会来杀你
Course, a stone can't kill you, either
但是 一旦你转移视线
but then you turn your head away.
然后你一眨眼
Then you blink.
这时 没错 它就能杀你
And, oh, yes, it can.
不要移开你的视线
Don't take your eyes off that.
那也是它们蒙上自己双眼的原因
That'.s why they cover their eyes.
它们不是在哭泣 而是不能冒险看到对方
They're not weeping, they can't risk looking at each other.
它们最强大的武器 也是它们最大的诅咒
Their greatest asset is their greatest curse.
它们永远都无法被看到
They can never be seen.
宇宙中最孤独的生物
Loneliest creatures in the universe.
我很抱歉 非常非常抱歉
Well, I'm sorry. I am very, very sorry.
现在全靠你自己了
It's up to you now.
我应该怎么做
What am I supposed to do?
那个蓝盒子 是我的时间机器
The blue box. It's my time machine.
那里拥有足够它们永久享用的巨大能量
There is a world of time energy in there they could feast on forever
但是也有可能产生毁天灭地的破坏力
but the damage they could do could switch off the sun.
你必须把它送来给我
You have got to send it back to me.
怎么送
How?
恐怕到头了
And that's it, I'm afraid.
抄本里没有下文了
There's no more from you on the transcript,
我只有这些
that's the last I've got.
我不清楚是什么让你停止谈话
I don't know what stopped you talking,
但我猜是它们来了
but I can guess. They're coming.
天使来找你们了
The angels are coming for you.
听好
But listen,
你的性命可能全靠这个了
your life could depend on this.
别眨眼 一下都不能眨 一眨眼你就会死
Don't blink. Don't even blink. Blink and you're dead.
它们很快 快的超出你的想像
They are fast. Faster than you can believe.
别转身 别回头 千万别眨眼
Don't turn your back, don't look away and don't blink.
祝你好运
Good luck.
不 不要 你不能
No, don't. You can't!
我把它倒回去
I'll rewind him.
倒回去有什么用
What good will that do?
你没有在盯着雕像
You're not looking at the statue.
你也没有
Neither are you.
盯着它
Looking at it.
一直盯着它
Keep looking at it.
只有一个 对吧
It's just one, right?
只有这一个
It's just this one.
只要一直盯着这个雕像
We're okay if we just keep staring at this one statue.
我们就会没事
Everything's gonna be fine.
还有三个
There's three more.
三个
Three?
它们之前在楼上
They were upstairs before
但我好像听到它们动了
but I think I heard them moving.
在哪里 三个 往哪里移动
Moving? Three of them? Moving where?
我去四处看看 检查一下
I'm gonna look around. I'm gonna check.
你一直盯着这个 别眨眼
You keep looking at this one. Don't blink.
记住他说的 千万别眨眼
Remember what he said. Don't even blink.
谁会眨眼 我害怕得眨不了眼了
Who blinked? I'm too scared to blink.
好吧 我们要去门口 前门
Okay, we're going to the door. Front door.
好吧 我们不能两个都去门口
Okay, we can't both get to the front door
这样就没人盯着那个东西 你留在这里
without taking our eyes off that thing, so you stay here.
什么
What?
我就在附近 你待在这里
I'll be just round the corner. You stay here.
它们把门锁住了 它们把我们锁在里面了
They've locked it! They've locked us in.
为什么
Why?
我有它们想要的东西
I've got something they want.
什么
What?
那把钥匙
The key.
我上次来这里拿到的
I took it last time I was here.
它们跟着我就是想拿回去
They followed me to get it back.
我带它们去到了蓝盒子那里
I led them to the blue box.
现在它们有了蓝盒子
Now they've got that.
把钥匙给它们吧
Give them the key.
我去看看后门 你在这里等着
I'm gonna check the back door. You wait here.
把钥匙给它们 它们想要就给它们吧
Give them the key! Give them what they want!
莎丽 不要 它们从后面过来怎么办
Sally, no! What if they come behind me?
坚持住
Hang on!
哦 天呐
God.
Oh, God.
锁住了
It's locked!
莎丽 莎丽
Sally! Sally!
打不开
It won't open!
莎丽 求你 我不行了
Sally, please, I can't do this!
莎丽 快点
Sally, hurry UP!
你在哪里
Where are you?
拉瑞
Larry,
它们锁住了后门 但这儿有个地下室
they've blocked up the back door, but there's a cellar.
那里也许有出路 送货口之类的
There might be a way out. Delivery hatch or something.
我来了
I'm coming!
我待不下去了
I can't stay here.
好吧 伙计们
Okay, boys.
我们知道原理
We know how this works.
只要我看着你们 你们就动不了
You can't move so long as I can see you.
博士说 亭子里有一整个世界
A whole world in the box, the Doctor says.
希望他没说谎
I hope he's not lying
因为我看不出哪里还有别的出路
'cause I don't see how else we're getting out.
噢 你那个也来了
Oh, and there's your one.
它为什么指向…
Why is it pointing at the…
灯
light?
天呐 它要关灯
Oh, my God, it's turning out the light!
快点
Quickly!
我找不到门锁
I can't find the lock!
莎丽 快点
Sally, hurry UP!
快打开
Get it open!
它们越来越快了 莎丽 快点
They're getting faster, Sally! Come on!
转不动
It won't turn!
转不了
I can't turn it!
莎丽
Sally!
莎丽 赶快
Sally, hurry up! Come on!
这是安全协议第712号
DOCTOR: This is Security Protocol 712.
这个时空舱探测到已授权的控制碟的存在
This time capsule has detected the presence of an authorised control disc
授权一次旅行机会
valid one journey.
请插入碟片并准备起飞
Please insert the disc and prepare for departure.
看上去像DVD播放器 有个插槽
Looks like a DVD player. There's a slot.
它们想闯进来
They're trying to get in!
那你快点啊
Well, hurry up, then!
怎么回事
What's happening?
天哪 它要把我们留在这儿
Oh, my God, it's leaving us behind.
博士 不要 你不能
Doctor, don't! You can't!
博士
Doctor!
盯着它们 快 盯着它们
Look at them! Quick, look at them!
我想我们不需要了
I don't think we need to.
他耍了它们 博士耍了它们
He tricked them. The Doctor tricked them.
它们在互相看着对方
They're looking at each other.
它们再也动不了了
They're never gonna move again.
一 年 之 后
你能照看一下店铺吗 我去隔壁买点牛奶
Can you mind the shop? I'm just nipping next door for some milk.
好的 不用担心
Yeah, no worries.
这是什么
What's this?
没什么
Nothing.
莎丽
Sally.
你就不能放手吗
Can't you let it go?
我当然没办法放手
Of course I can't let it go.
都过去了
This is over.
博士要怎么知道去哪里的墙上写那些话
How did the Doctor know where to write those words on the wall?
他怎么得到抄本的
How could he get a copy of the transcript?
他是从哪里得到那些信息的
Where did he get all that information from?
听着 有些事情你永远无法弄明白 但那没关系
Look, some things you never find out and that's okay.
不 有关系
No, it isn't.
有没有想过这会阻碍一些
Ever think this might be getting in the way of
其他事情
other things?
我们只是一起开店
We just run a shop together.
仅此而已 只是开店
That's all it is, just a shop.
总之…
Anyway.
牛奶
Milk.
一会儿就回来
Back in a mo.
没错 肯定是这条路
Right, it's definitely this way.
博士 博士 博士
Doctor! Doctor! Doctor!
你好 对不起 有点急事
Hello. Sorry, bit of a rush.
有件很重要的事我们得去阻止
There's a sort of thing happening. Very important that we stop it.
天哪 是你
Oh, my God, it's you.
真的是你
It really is you.
你不记得我了吗
Oh, you don't remember me, do you?
博士 我们没时间耽误了 迁移已经开始了
Doctor, we haven't got time for this. Migration's started.
听着 很抱歉 我的生活有点复杂
Look, sorry, I've got a bit of a complex life.
我身上发生的事情总是不按顺序来的
Things don't always happen to me in quite the right order.
经常搞得我很困惑
Gets a bit confusing at times,
尤其是结婚 我对结婚很不在行
especially at weddings. I'm rubbish at weddings,
尤其是我自己的
Iespecially my own.
天呐 对啊
Oh, my God, of course!
你是个时间旅行者
You're a time traveller.
那些事还没发生在你身上 全都没有
It hasn't happened to you yet, none of it.
还在你的未来
It's still in your future.
什么还没发生
What hasn't happened?
博士快点 还有20分钟到警戒线
Doctor, please! 20 minutes to hatching.
是我
It was me!
天呐 从一开始就是我
Oh, for God's sake, it was me all along.
你是从我这里得到的
You got it all from me.
得到什么
Got what?
好吧 听着
Okay, listen.
有一天你会被困在1969年
One day, you're gonna get stuck in 1969.
确保把这个带在你身边
Make sure you've got this with you.
你会需要它的
You're gonna need it.
博士
Doctor!
好的 听着 我得赶紧了
Yeah! Listen, listen, gotta dash.
有大事发生
Things happening.
其实是四件事
Well, four things.
好吧 四件事还有一只蜥蜴
Well, four things and a lizard.
好吧 别担心
Okay, no worries.
你去吧 某天再见
On you go. See you around some day.
你叫什么名字
What was your name?
莎丽·斯帕罗
Sally Sparrow
很高兴见到你 莎丽·斯帕罗
Good to meet you, Sally Sparrow.
再见 博士
Goodbye, Doctor.
麻雀和夜莺
古籍和稀有DVD商店
别眨眼
Don't blink.
一眨眼你就会死
Blink and you're dead.
别转身
Don't turn your back.
别回头
Don't look away.
千万别眨眼
And don't blink.
祝你好运
Good luck.
我们要去宇宙的尽头
We're going to the end of the universe.
下集预告
呼唤穿越星际而来 一遍又一遍
The call came from across the stars, over and over again
"来到乌托邦"
"Come to Utopia."
博士
Doctor.
上校
Captain.
是未来族
It's a future time.
乌托邦是什么
Utopia is…
最后一批人类在晚上散开了
The last of the humans, scattered across the night.
人类要来了
Humans are coming.
即使时间领主也不该走到这么远
Not even us Time Lords came this far.
我们应该走了
We should leave.